<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of in the generall visitation of the right vvorshipfull M. Robert White, Bachelour in Divinity, Arch-deacon of Norfolke, anno Domini 163[3?]</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Norfolk.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10280.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2642</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24439913</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24439913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27669</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27669)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1850:83)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of in the generall visitation of the right vvorshipfull M. Robert White, Bachelour in Divinity, Arch-deacon of Norfolke, anno Domini 163[3?]</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Norfolk.</author>
                  <author>White, Robert, Archdeacon of Norfolk.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Badger,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1633]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date altered in manuscript to 163[4]; date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:27669:1"/>
            <head>The Forme of the Oath to be adminiſtred <hi>to the Church-wardens and Sworn-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu ſhall ſweare, that all hope of gaine, feare and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſet aſide, you make true preſentment of all ſuch parties as have offended againſt theſe Articles, or are vehemently ſuſpected, famed or reported ſo to have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: So helpe you God, and the Contents of the holy Goſpels.</p>
            <closer>God ſave the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27669:1"/>
            <head>Concerning the Church of England.</head>
            <p>ARe there any in your Pariſh that being Popiſhly affected, doe derogate from his Maieſties ſupremacie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall? &amp; who be they?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Are there any in your Pariſh that out of factious and ſchiſmaticall ſpirits doe affirme that this Church of England by law eſtabliſhed vnder the Kings Maieſtie, is not a true and Apoſtolicall Church, teaching and maintaining the doctrine of the Apoſtles?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Are there any in your pariſh that affirme that the forme of Gods worſhip in the Church of England, eſtabliſhed by the law, and contained in the booke of Common prayer, &amp; adminiſtration of Sacraments, is a corrupt, ſuperſtitious, or vnlawfull worſhip of God, or containeth any thing in it that is repugnant to the Scriptures?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Are there any in your Pariſh that affirme that any of the 39 Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon by the Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops of both prouinces, and the whole Clergie in the Conuocation holden at London, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1562. are in any part ſuperſtitious or erronious or ſuch as with good conſcience they may not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Are there any in your Pariſh that affirme that the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, by Law eſtabliſhed are wicked, Antichriſtian or ſuperſtitious, or ſuch as being commanded by lawfull authority, men that are zealouſly and godlily affected, may not with good conſcience approue them, vſe them, or ſubſcribe vnto them?</p>
            <p n="6">6 Are there any in your pariſh that affirme, that the gouernment of the Church of England vnder his Maieſtie by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons and the reſt that beare office in the ſame is Antichriſtian or repugnant to the word of God?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Are there any in your pariſh that impugne the forme or manner of making and conſecrating Biſhops Prieſts or deacons, vſed in the Church of England?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Are there in your Pariſh, any Schiſmaticall Separatiſts, new combined brotherhoods, deprauers of ſuch as conforme themſelues to the doctrine, gouernment, rites and Ceremonies of the Church of England, or any ſecret maintainers and fauourers of ſuch ſeparatiſts and new brotherhoods? Are there any Corner Conuenticles, or any that maintaine or fauour or defend them? Are there any ſuch factious people in your pariſh, that diſliking the gouernment of the Church of England, take vpon themſelues the name of Church, and make orders rules or other conſtitutions to be obſerued and kept by themſelues.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſtrie, Service and Sacraments.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether are the common Prayers ſaid or ſung by your Miniſter, both Morning and Euening diſtinctly, and reuerently euery ſunday and
<pb facs="tcp:27669:2"/> holy-day, and on their Eues, and at couenient and vſuall times of thoſe dayes, and in moſt conuenient place for the edifying of the people?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether doth your Miniſter obſerue the orders Rites and Ceremonies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Booke of common Prayer, in reading the Holy Scriptures prayers and adminiſtration of Sacraments, without diminiſhing, or adding any thing in the matter or forme thereof?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether doth your Miniſter on wedneſdayes and frydayes not being holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, at the accuſtomed houres of ſeruice reſorte to the Church and ſay the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany: and other prayers preſcribed? And doth your Clerke or Sexton giue warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before by tolling of a Bell on thoſe dayes, and doth one perſon of euery houſe repaire to the Church at thoſe times uſually, and there ſtay according to the Cannon?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether doth your Miniſter leauing the uſe of the Font Chriſten or bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize in any Baſon or other prophane veſſels? doth your Miniſter baptize or Chriſten any out of the face of the Church and Congregation, or at any other time then upon ſundayes or holy-dayes without ſpeciall cauſe, or without Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and God-mothers? Are any perſons admitted to anſwer as God-fathers or God-mothers at the Chriſtning of any Child, except he or ſhe haue before recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Holy Communion? doth your Miniſter in Baptizing of Children obſerue the orders, Rites and Ceremonies, appointed in the Booke of Common prayer without addition omiſſion or innovation?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Doe you know any Parents that deferre the Chriſtning of their Children, or any that haue not had their Children Chriſtned at their owne Pariſh Church or Chappell? what is the cauſe that they keepe them ſo long vnchriſtned? doe you know of any parents that haue had their children priuatly Baptized, either by a Popiſh prieſt contrary to the Lawes of the Church of England, or by an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Miniſter omitting any part of the forme of Baptizing Children con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Booke of common prayer?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Doth your Miniſter giue warning publikly in the Church at Morning prayer, the ſunday before he adminiſtreth the Communion for the better prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the pariſhioners?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doth your Miniſter as oft as he adminiſtreth the Communion, firſt receiue it himſelfe? doth he uſe any bread or wine newly brought, before the words of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution be rehearſed and the bread and wine preſent on the Communion table? doth he not deliuer the bread and wine to euery Communicant ſeuerally?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Hath your Miniſter admitted to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion any that be openly knowne to liue in ſome notorious offence or Crime without repentance or ſatiſfaction of the Congregatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or who hath openly and maliciouſly contended with his or her Neighbours, before hée or ſhée haue openly and charitably reconciled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againe and remitted all rancour and malice, whatſoeuer Controuerſie hath beene betweene them?</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27669:2"/>9 Doth your Miniſter adminiſter the Communion to any but ſuch as knéele, or doe any refuſe to knéele? hath he adminiſtred to any who refuſe to be preſent at publick prayer, or who hath depraued the Booke of Common Prayer, admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments or the Rites and Ceremonies preſcribed, or the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion agréed upon, or the Booke of Ordering Prieſts and Biſhops, or againſt his Maieſties ſupremacy? haue any béene for theſe cauſes repelled, and haue they repented in writing or otherwiſe and what be their names?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Hath your Miniſter more benefices then one? if he hath how farre diſtant are they? and whether ſerues he two Cures or not? when he is abſent, hath he an allowed Preacher for his Curat?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Hath your Church or Chappell béene deſtitute of a Curate, and how long, and by whoſe default? hath any Curate ſerued or doth any Curate ſerue without lycence of the Ordinary?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Doe you know any Popiſh Prieſts, Seminaries, Ieſuits, or Runnagate perſons that doe preach, ſay Maſſe or miniſter any Popiſh Sacraments or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, or elſe doe reſort ſecretly or openly unto your pariſh, and what be their names, and unto whoſe houſes doe they reſort, and of whome are they harboured and reléeued? ſet downe their Names and Sir-names?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Is your Parſon Vicar or Curate or any other parſon in your pariſh a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer of the Romiſh Church or Religion, or of any other ſect or Schiſmaticall opinion, or hath he or doth he maintaine or teach any doctrine contrary or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to any of the Articles agréed vpon by the Clergie in the Conuocation holden at <hi>London Anno Dom.</hi> 1562? haue they taught publikly or ſecretly any doctrine tending to the diſcredit and diſpraiſe either of the Booke of Common prayer, or of the Preachers and Miniſters of the word and Sacraments, or of the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued order for gouernment by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops Deanes, Arch-deacons and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Officers in the Church of England, or make any other innouation? Or haue they permitted any man ſo teaching, or making innouation in ſuch manner?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Is your Miniſter an allowed Preacher, if he be not, doth he procure euery moneth a Sermon to be Preached in his Cure by Preachers lawfully licenced? And on euery Sunday when there is no Sermon, doth he or his Curate reade ſome one of the homilies preſcribed?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Doth your Miniſter alwaies in ſaying the publike prayers and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacraments weare a decent Surplice with ſleeues, and being a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duate, doth he weare alwaies there-with an Hoode by the order of the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties agréeable to his degrée?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Hath your Miniſter, or any other Preacher in your Church, Preached any thing to confute or impugne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any doctrine deliuered by any other Preacher? and doth he alwaies before the Sermon, Lecture, and homilie pray for Chriſts Catholike Church, The <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> and our Gracious <hi>Queene Mary,</hi> the Noble <hi>Prince Charles,</hi> the <hi>Lady Mary,</hi> the <hi>Lady Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>Her Princely Iſſue,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27669:3"/> The Miniſters of Gods Holy word, as well Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, as other Paſtours and Curats, for the <hi>Kings</hi> moſt Honourable Councell, the Nobility and Magiſtrates of this Realme and the Commons? And doth he alwaies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his prayer with the Lords prayer, According to the Cannon 55?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Hath or doth any ſtrange Preacher preach in your Church which refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to conforme himſelfe to the Lawes, rites and Ordinances eſtabliſhed, or which hath not firſt ſhewed a ſufficient licence?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Doth your Miniſter in his Sermons 4 times in the yeare at leaſt, teach and declare the <hi>Kings</hi> Maieſties power within his Realmes to be the higheſt power vnder God, to whom all within the ſame owe iuſt loyalty &amp; obedience, and that all forraine power is iuſtly taken away?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Doth your Miniſter euery Sunday halfe an hower before euening prayer or more, examine and inſtruct the youth of the pariſh in the Catechiſme ſet forth in the Booke of Common prayer? And doe the Church-wardens aſſiſt the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter héerein? and who be they that refuſe to be Catechized? and what Parents haue not diligently ſent their Children and ſeruants to be Catechized?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Hath your Miniſter Married any without licence in the times prohibited, and hath he married any without licence whoſe banes haue not béene openly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Church 3 ſeuerall ſundayes or holydayes? if any of the parties dwell out of the pariſh, hath he married them without Certificate vnder the Miniſters hand of the other pariſh, that the banes of matrimony haue béene lawfully asked and publiſhed without contradiction? hath he married any at any other times of the day, then betwéene the howers of 8 and 12 in the forenoone, or in any priuate houſe, or when there is no licence before the Parents and Gouerners (the parties being vnder the age of 21 yeares) haue teſtified their conſent?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Hath your Miniſter declared euery ſunday to the people at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed what holy-dayes and faſting dayes be the weeke following? doth he, being a Preacher, conferre with all Recuſants and perſons Excommunicated and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, to reduce them to the vnity of the Church?</p>
               <p n="22">22 Doth your Miniſter kéepe a note of all Excommunicated perſons within your Pariſh, and once euery ſix months doth he denounce them which haue not obtained their abſolution on ſome ſunday in ſeruice time, that others may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to refraine their company?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Is your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate dilligent in viſiting the ſicke and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting them? doe they bury your dead in ſuch Chriſtian and comely manner, as is preſcribed in the booke of Common prayer? hath any layman, other then a lawfull Miniſter taken vpon him to bury the dead contrary to order?</p>
               <p n="24">24 Hath your Miniſter refuſed to baptize any child brought to the Church, or to bury any Corps brought to the Church, or Churchyard, or to Church any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hauing had conuenient warning thereof?</p>
               <p n="25">25 Hath your Miniſter, being truly informed of the danger of death of any
<pb facs="tcp:27669:3"/> Child vnbaptized, and being deſired to goe to the place where the Childe is, to Baptize it, neglected to goe, by meanes whereof the Child dyed vnbaptized?</p>
               <p n="26">26 Haue you any Lecture in your Pariſh continued without lawfull licence of the Biſhop? doth your Lecturer obſerue all the rites ſpecified in the 56 Canon?</p>
               <p n="27">27 Doth your Miniſter at any time preach or adminiſter the Communion in any priuate houſe, except when any are ſo impotent that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not go to Church, or are very dangerouſly ſicke?</p>
               <p n="28">28 Doe any Chaplaines in your pariſh preach or adminiſter the Communion in any Chappell not conſecrated, or in any houſe hauing no Chappell allowed by law? doe the Lords and Maſters that haue priuate Chappels of their owne, reſort often to the pariſh Church and there receiue the Communion, at the leaſt once euery yeare?</p>
               <p n="29">29 Doth your Miniſter reſide vpon his Parſonage or Vicarage houſe?</p>
               <p n="30">30 Hath there béene any ſecret Conuenticles or méetings in your pariſh by any Prieſts, Miniſters, or others, tending to the deprauation of the forme of prayer, doctrine, or gouerment of this Church of England?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Church, Church-yard, Parſonage, and Vicarage houſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether is your Church, Chappell, and Chancell, well and ſufficiently repaired in the walls and roofe, the ſeates conuenient, the floore paued, the windowes glazed, and all theſe cleanely kept? Is the Manſion houſe of your Parſon or Vicar with the buildings thereunto belonging, well and ſufficiently repaired, and your Church-yard walls, Railes or pales kept in good repare?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hath your Church or Church-yard béene abuſed &amp; prophaned by any fighting, chiding, brawling, or quarelling, any playes, lords of miſ-rule, Summer lords, Morris-dauncers, Pedlers, Bowlers, Bearewards, Butchers, Feaſts, Schooles, Temporall Courts or Léets, Lay Iuries, Muſters, or other prophane vſage? Haue any Bells béene ſuperſtitiouſly rung on holy-dayes, or their Eues, or at any other times, without good cauſe allowed by the Miniſter and Church-wardens? haue any trées béene fell'd in the Church-yard and by whom?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Are your Almeſ-houſes, Church-houſes &amp; ſchoole-houſes or other houſes and buildings ſet vpon the ſoile of the Church or Church-yard ſufficiently repaired maintained and to godly and right vſe imployed?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Haue you in your Church or Chappell all things neceſſary for Common prayer and other Rites of the Church, as the Bible in the largeſt volume, the Booke of Comon Prayer lately authorized by his Maieſty, the Bookes of homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies allowed, a conuenient Pulpit for preaching, a decent ſeate for the Miniſter to reade ſeruice in, conueniently placed, a ſtrong Cheſt with thrée lockes and thrée keyes, one for the Miniſter, the other for the Church-wardens for the kéeping of the Regiſter Booke of the Chriſtnings, marriages and Burials, and a poore mans box conueniently ſet néere the Church doore?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Haue you in your Church a Font of ſtone, for Baptiſme ſet in the ancient,
<pb facs="tcp:27669:4"/> vſuall place, a decent Table for the Communion, conueniently placed, couered with ſilke or other decent ſtuffe in time of diuine ſeruice, and with a faire linnen cloth ouer that, at the adminiſtration of the Communion?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Haue you all ſuch Bells, Ornaments and other Vtenſils as haue anciently belonged to your Church, a Communion Cup of Siluer with a Couer, a faire ſtanding Pot of Pewter or purer mettal for the wine vpon the Communion table a comely Surpleſſe with ſleeues, and a Booke of the names of all ſtrange Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſubſcribed with their names, and the name of the Biſhop or others where they had licence?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Haue you a booke of parchment for a Regiſter books, of Mariages, Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and Burials? Are wéekely the names and Sur-names of all perſons mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, chriſtned, and buried, and of their parents with the day and yeare written fairely in the ſayd parchment booke? Is euery leafe (being full) ſubſcribed by you the Miniſter and Church-wardens?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Haue you in the Eaſt-end of the Church the tenne Commandements fairly written and ſet up, and other choſen ſentences of the holy Scripture written vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conuenient places of the wals? Is there a table of the degrees of mariage ſett up? Haue you ſeates enough in the Church for the pariſhioners to fit on, and are they in good repaire?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Eccleſiaſticall Courts.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HAth the Officiall, or his ſurrogate, or any other exerciſing Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction in this Archdeaconrie, their Regiſters, or Actuaries, Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or Sumners, at any time wincked at, and ſuffered any Adulteries, Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Inceſts, or other faults or offences to paſſe and remaine vnpuniſhed and vncorrected, or haue they commuted any pennance of ſuch offendors?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hath your Regiſter, his deputy, or ſubſtitute, ſet vp two Tables of the rates of Fées; one in the vſuall place or Conſiſtory where the Court is kept, and the other in his Regiſtry; and both of them in ſuch ſort, as euery man whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth may come to the view and peruſall thereof? Or if ſuch Tables haue heretofore béene ſet up, hath your Regiſter remoued the ſame, or ſuffered them to be remoued, hidden, or any wayes hindred from ſight?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Doe you know any houſholder or other perſon whatſoeuer, within your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or Chappelrie, that is deceaſed, that haue made their laſt wills and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the ſame not being yet proued; or if without will, who haue entred vpon their goods without lawfull adminiſtration taken from the Ordinary or other Iudge competent?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Schoole-maſters.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HAue you in your Pariſh any Schoole-maſters, who teach either in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſchoole or in priuate houſe? Is he reputed to be of ſound faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? Doth he giue any euill example of life? Is he allowed by the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnder his hand and ſeale? Or doth your Miniſter or Curate teach, and is he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in like manner?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27669:4"/>2 Doth your Miniſter or Schoole-maſter who teacheth, teach the Catechiſme by authority ſet forth? Doth hee when there is any Sermon, or diuine Seruice bring his ſchollers to Church, and ſée them quietly and ſoberly ordered? Doth hée examine them after their returne what they haue learned of the Sermon?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Pariſh clarke, and Sexton.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HAue you a pariſh-clerke appointed by the Miniſter, ſufficient for his place, of the age of twenty yeares at leaſt. Is he of honeſt conuerſation? Can he reade, write, and ſing? Is he diligent in his office, and ſeruiceable to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in time of diuine Seruice, and otherwiſe?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Doth your Clerke meddle with any thing aboue his office, as churching of women, burying the dead, reading of prayers, or ſuch like?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Doth your Clerk or Sexton kéep your Church cleane, the doores ſafe locked? Is any thing by his default loſt or ſpoiled in the Church, doth he ſuffer any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable ringing, or any prophane exerciſe in the Church.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Doth any of your Pariſh refuſe to pay vnto the Pariſh-clerke or Sexton, ſuch wages as are vnto them due, and haue beene accuſtomably payd?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning pariſhioners.</head>
               <p n="1">1 DOth any in your Pariſh prophane, violate, or miſpend the Sabbath or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidayes or any part of them, vſing any offenſiue conuerſation, or worldly labour in thoſe dayes or any of them?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Hath any in your Pariſh in time of diuine Seruice couered his head, albeit he hath infirmity, in which caſe a Cap is allowed? Is there any who hath not reuerently knéeled when the generall Confeſſion, Letany, and other prayers are read, and which haue not ſtood vp at the ſaying of the Beléefe?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Hath any in your Pariſh diſturbed diuine Seruice, by walking, talking, or any other way; or departed out of the Church during the Seruice, or Sermon, without ſome vrgent cauſe or loitered about the Church or Church-porch?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Are there any in your Pariſh, either man or woman, being aboue ſixteene yeares of age, that hath not receiued the holy Communion thrice at leaſt euery yeare, whereof once at Eaſter? Or haue any receiued the Communion in any other Pariſh Church or Chappell than their owne?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Doth any parent anſwer as God-father for his owne childe? Hath any God-father or God-mother made any other anſwer or ſpéech than is preſcribed in the booke?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Doe all fathers, mothers, maſters, miſtriſſes, come, and cauſe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeruants, and Apprentices, to come duly to the Church, and according to the Miniſters direction, to be inſtructed and catechiſed; or who be they that haue not obeyed the Miniſter herein?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Haue any perſons maried together within the degrées prohibited, ſet forth in a table appointed to be in euery Church?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Haue any perſons once lawfully maried together forſaken each other, or doe
<pb facs="tcp:27669:5"/> liue aſunder without the authority of the Ordinary? Or doe any being diuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or ſeparated marry againe, the former husband or wife yet liuing?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Hath any in your Pariſh vnreuerently vſed your Miniſter, or haue any laid violent hands vpon him, or diſgraced his office and calling by word or deed?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Haue you in your Pariſh any dweller or ſoiourner, a maintainer of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh doctrine, or ſuſpected to keepe or diſperſe ſchiſmaticke bookes, or to fauour any hereſie or error?</p>
               <p n="11">11 Haue any in time of diuine Seruice opened their ſhops, exerciſed their trades, vſed any gaming, béene in any Tauerne or Ale-houſe or otherwiſe ill imployed?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Are there in your Pariſh any adulterers, fornicators, inceſtuous perſons, bawdes, receiuers, or cloſe fauourers, conueiers away or ſufferers of any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent perſons to depart vnpuniſhed; or any which haue their méetings in priuate places in the night time or other vndecent times, and by reaſon thereof are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly defamed or vehemently ſuſpected of any of the ſaid crimes?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Is the fifth of Nouember kept holy, and thanksgiuing made to God for his Maieſties and the States happy deliuerance, according to the Ordinance in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Are there in your Pariſh any blaſphemers, common ſwearers, ribaudes, and ſuch as commonly vſe bawdy, immodeſt, vnciuill, and filthy ſpéeches, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſlanderers, ſcolds, common drunkards, or any defamed of any of the ſaid crimes?</p>
               <p n="15">15 Doe any in your Pariſh adminiſter the goods of the dead without authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or ſuppreſſe their Will and Teſtament? Haue any Executors neglected to performe the wils of the dead, eſpecially in paying of Legacies giuen to the Church, to the poore, or to any other charitable or godly vſes?</p>
               <p n="16">16 Doe any refuſe to pay to the reparations, ornaments, and other things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in your Church, as they are ceſſed or taxed?</p>
               <p n="17">17 Haue any in your Pariſh béene chriſtned, churched, buried, or receiued the Communion; or béene maried out of your Pariſh, both parties dwelling in your Pariſh?</p>
               <p n="18">18 Haue all women in your Pariſh deliuered of child, come at conuenient time after to Church to giue thankes? And haue they béene Churched according to the forme of the booke of Common Prayer?</p>
               <p n="19">19 Hath the perambulation of the circuit of your Pariſh béene obſerued once euery yeare at the vſuall time? If not, by whoſe default?</p>
               <p n="20">20 Haue any in your Pariſh giuen to the Church-wardens or Side-men or any of them euill words, for doing their Office according to their Oath, and conſcience in making preſentment for any default?</p>
               <p n="21">21 Is there any man or woman in your Pariſh that vſeth witchcraft, ſorcery charmes, or vnlawfull prayer, or incantations in Latine, or Engliſh, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:27669:5"/> vpon any Chriſten body or beaſt, or any that reſorteth to ſuch perſons for counſell or helpe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Church-wardens and Sworne-men.</head>
               <p n="1">1 DOe any in your Pariſh take vpon them to bee Church-warden or Sideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which is not lawfully choſen by the Miniſter and Pariſhioners ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Canon? Doe any continue that office longer than one yeare, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be choſen againe; and are al ſuch officers choſen yearely in Eaſter-wéek?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Do your Church-wardens within one moneth at the moſt after their yeare ended, before the Miniſter and Pariſhioners, giue vp a iuſt account of all ſuch money, and other things as they haue receiued and beſtowed? Haue they deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all remaining in their hands, belonging to the Church or Pariſh, to the next Church-wardens?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Haue the Church-wardens with the aduice of the Miniſter from time to time, prouided a ſufficient quantity of fine white bread and wholeſome wine for the number of communicants? Haue you at euery Communion collected the deuotion of the Communicants, and put it into the poore-mans-box?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Doe the Church-wardens and ſworne-men before euery viſitation, and at other times when there is iuſt occaſion, meete and conferre about their preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and who hath (after notice giuen him of the time and place) careleſly abſented himſelfe?</p>
               <p n="5">5 Is the forfeiture of twelue pence for abſence from the Church appointed by ſtate for the vſe of the poore, taken and leuyed by the Church-wardens, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed according to the ſaid ſtatute? Is the ſame forfeiture taken of all perſons which ſtand wilfully ſuſpended or excommunicated?</p>
               <p n="6">6 Haue any Church-wardens loſt, ſold, changed, or retained, any goods, orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or bels, rents, or implements of the Church, without ſpeciall licence of the Ordinary?</p>
               <p n="7">7 Doe you the Church-wardens and Swornemen about the midſt of Diuine ſeruice vſually walke out of the Church, and ſee who are abroad in any Ale-houſe or elſe where abſent, or euill imployed: and haue you preſented all ſuch to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Doe you know or haue heard of any fame, or offence committed, or duty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by any of your Pariſh before your time, and heretofore not preſented by the former Church-wardens to the Ordinary, and as yet not reformed, and haue you preſented the ſame?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
